[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gregory cap Hammer
today's guest is idar Friedman he's the
CEO and co-founder of codium AI immar
and his team develop a whole bunch of
cool automated testing tools and they
use generative AI techniques like large
language models iter welcome to the show
hey very nice being here thank you so
much for inviting me we're glad to talk
to you today about an open-source tool
that you've developed at codium aai
called cover agent cover agent is based
on a paper that was published at the
foundations of software engineering
conference let's start by exploring some
of the features that cover agent
provides and how it works are you ready
to dive in yeah of course okay so at the
start I'm going to read a quotation that
comes from the documentation for the
cover agent tool and then we're going to
use this sentence to explore more about
how the tool works so the sentence is as
follows it says codium AI cover agent
aims to efficiently increase code
coverage by automatically generating
qualified tests to enhance existing test
Suites so let's start at a high level
can you explain what are the testing
tasks that cover agent automatically
performs yeah so I guess you're mainly
referring to types of testing like is it
unit testing component testing
integration testing Etc so basically I
think that cover agent can try to
generate all of these but The Sweet Spot
that we saw is mostly around component
testing if you provide an initial few
test that cover one or more components
and you run cover agent it will try to
generate many more actually it will try
to generate as many as it could until
reaching your criteria like for example
until a certain threshold was met or a
certain iteration that you define that
you don't want to run more than a few
iteration because there's also a cost
that comes together basically what cover
agent does it takes the first few tests
that was given as part of the test suite
and is exploiting these to inspire it to
generate more so if you will come with
integration test or end to end tests of
different types it could be like end to
test in playright or Cypress Etc it will
try to mimic that if you come with a few
simple component tests it will try to
mimic that integration test Etc so you
can aim and try to generate any type of
testing having said that it works the
best for component testing at the moment
like with the current implementation
July 24 so you said it works best with
component testing when you say component
is that equivalent to talking about unit
testing yes like the reason I prefer the
term component because I think it makes
it clear that you can do more than four
lines of code you know than what you
expect from a simple method or something
like that if you're doing clean code of
course and if you have for example a
class that could have 500 lines of code
with just just an example like five
methods actually I think you will be
more happier be more satisfied running
cover agent on that because it's within
the limit of cover agent from what we
see technically and experimenting with
it empirically to generate good test for
that for this kind of setup and I think
that provide more value of course it's a
matter of taste and also situation some
people they have better appetite for
specific methods like unit test because
for different reason they want them to
be fast they want to verify that each
specific method is being highly tested
or some would prefer like going one
level above like which is a component in
many cases you gain a lot of the
properties of unit test they're still
fast they're still like independent and
things like that but you have more
opportunities for interesting you know
behaviors that are capturing more of
what the software is supposed to do
so yes so like I believe that component
testing is the way to go and cover agent
covers that quite nicely so that's why
it's our recommendation but you can go
with unit test as well considering our
terminology of course okay thanks for
that response it was really helpful now
just a moment ago you mentioned this
idea of increasing code coverage can you
talk briefly what is code coverage in
the context of cover agent and why is it
a good idea to increase code coverage
right so code coverage in the most
simple like terminology is considering a
test suite and considering a set of
files method classes packages you want
to cover you want to check how much of
the lines will come back to this notion
how many of these lines are being
covered by the test Suite so just an
example let's say you have a test Suite
of including five tests and you have two
files with each one have two components
and each one has 100 lines Okay so 400
lines you want to check like the
coverage will report the coverage report
will tell you how many of these 500
lines are being covered by these five
tests it could also tell you like a
breakdown in most cases like depends on
the package that you're using to create
the coverage report in most cases like
it would tell you like each method or
each package or each files like the
coverage of that specific component a
specific item and then lastly I want to
say that we did talk about like line
coverage when I explained myself I
talked about line coverage like how many
lines are covered that's like the basic
metric here but there are other types of
coverage for example there could be
Branch coverage Branch coverage there
could be others but just as an example
Branch coverage means how well we're
covering each one of the branches in the
code for example an if statement could
have two branches and you could in line
coverage if you pass this if statement
great plus one but in Branch coverage
you want to check if you passed zero
then it's 0% of this line one then it's
50% or two of the options of this Branch
then it's 100% by the way if statement
could have as many as statement it's not
only one or two and that's really
interesting the reason I want to double
click on the branch coverage because I
think like there's a huge it was really
hard to work with Branch coverage but
actually llm opens opportunity to work
with Branch coverage for two reasons
first Sometimes LM can help you describe
Branch coverage and natural language
description like sometimes it's like
hard to say like which part of the
branch if it's a large if statement
which part of it how are you passing it
llm can help you describe the natural
language description and the second
thing is like usually to pass through
each one of the branches it's really
hard to generate those type of tests and
we'll probably cover it a bit later and
llm can help also on that thanks for
that response you mentioned things about
llms and we're going to dive into to how
cover agent uses llms later in our
discussion you talked about code
coverage and you mentioned Branch
coverage and statement coverage both of
those sound like higher is better
metrics where getting more code coverage
is better than less is that the right
way to think of it many would say that
code coverage is axy metric I think
Almost 100% people would say that but I
think that also some percentage of
developers and managers would say that
code coverage is actually a vanity
metric practically what we're trying to
say is that did we check that the code
work exactly as expected okay and now
how do you check that supposedly you
have a spec and if the spec describes
any possible usage of your code
basically you can try to convert this
spec into like tests comprehensively
like one to one like fully complet
complete translate of your spec into
test and then who cares about what's the
line coverage rather you actually tested
all the options I'm not talking only
like when I saying like 100% spec
specification I'm also talking about
like edge cases and bad cases anything
that could eventually happen to your
software any data processing any
software runtime that can happen so who
cares about line coverage the question
is can you write that that kind of spec
can you simulate that kind of of
situation and in most cases and even in
the harshest like and the hardware where
is maybe even simpler in the case of
military or space where you really want
to it's still very hard and then the
question what's your alternative so if
you can say that you covered 100% of the
lines then you're probably in a good
place proxy wise because you probably
like pass through all the options or
a lot of the options having said that I
just gave an example where maybe you
passed through some if statement and
maybe this if statement leads you to the
next line but it could lead you there in
many different ways and probably you
want to check each one of them if you
want to like Perfection IE your your
testing and then you want to go like
different types of Branch coverage and
statement coverage like things that you
mentioned but even then it could be a
proxy and even like vanity but I think
these days
nobody until today invented something
better so the higher is better because
you probably tested more more statement
more use cases more flows of your
software having said that I think
there's opportunities for llm also to
change that but that's like a different
answer so I'll wait a second and just to
finalize I want to say that there are
other metrics like for example there is
the mutation testing metric but I think
most of them the industry the standard
will say that are complementary to code
coverage okay that's really helpful so
you've mentioned statement coverage and
Branch coverage and I think the
intuition there is if you don't cover
the code you'll never know whether or
not there was a bug in the code because
you didn't run it in the first place is
that the right way to think about code
coverage yeah I agree like basically
okay maybe back to fundamentals code
coverage is in most cases is not being
measured or tested or reported with some
semantic analysis like symbolic
execution or something like that it's
usually being measured by actually
running a test that actually running the
code of the test and that actually
eventually or it could be like running
the test doesn't have to be code like if
it's a integration testing Etc it might
be like API calls or something like with
a script or with some UI but eventually
it means running the test that actually
makes your software run and then right
it's a simple way to say like if you
checked each line if you checked a
specific line hence you ran the software
such that this line is being executed
you decrease the chance that that line
has a bug but you know it actually
doesn't really like necessarily say that
let me give you an example a test is
usually it's composed of like what is
the data you want to run through your
software and then could be some Logic
for man manipulating your software or
manipulating the data and then receiving
the output of your software and then
checking that output basically you can
do a mistake and do really bad like
checks and practically the line was
executed of the line of the code that
you want to check was executed hence the
coverage report will say done clear but
you didn't really test it let me give
you an example let's say I'm writing a
test of A Sort function and I'm writing
like here is an array and I'm running
the array and 1 2 4 3 and I'm getting
back the result and I'm checking that
the array is like I'm doing a property
based testing which is not bad and I'm
checking that the output of the sort is
four the length is four right and the
sort function might bring me back one
two 2 two it's not the right accurate
the test coverage could be even 100% or
close to it and it's not working and
we're all like happy but no the sword
function doesn't work so the fact that
we pass through a line is not enough so
although you just got really like simply
I think like it's a bit more complicated
and that's why coverage is also
complicated and people say it's like
sometimes proxy or vanity yeah that was
a great response so I think what you're
saying is that coverage is a proxy it's
helpful but it can't be the final answer
now let's turn a little bit to the
coverage agent implementation yeah so
where does coverage agent come into play
in the story that you were just telling
about testing a sorting algorithm great
so in many ways I won't double click on
all explain all and let's chat so first
you know writing tests and thinking
about tapy paths and edge cases is a
tedious task like if you want to get to
above 80% code coverage even in a simple
like method go I'm not saying that this
is what you need to do it's not my call
to action but go to chat
and ask for give me some you know snake
game or whatever more than 100 lines of
code but not to more than that and then
try to start generating tests that will
you know cover more than 80% it could be
quite challenging so it's a tedious task
like to think about everything so first
you can use cover agent first you need
to come up yourself with a few tests and
then like after probably that will be
quite easy you know just thinking about
some a few simple tests it could be even
a
and then the first thing that cover
agent will help you is generate a bunch
of of tests if you give it a good prompt
sometimes even without prompting it
there is a prompt option it's aiming to
generate edge cases and like
complimentary tests and help you think
about your testing eventually by the way
although a test Suite is supposed to
reach to high code coverage you can
choose not to take all the tests and
like you just shorten your time to think
about those tests and think about those
edge cases and then like okay these two
seem too simple these two I don't like
because you know there's some test
smells there's code smell but there's
still test smells Etc by the way a
Shameless plug if you need to generate
this few first tests and you're also
either lazy or want to use AI for that
that's one of our other tools like cod
AI ID plugin for V code or jet Brains
it's called code youate by the way the
ID plugin helps you exactly with there's
a few tests that's one point that I
mentioned like just help you with more
Edge case Etc but ideally cover agent
would have the right Frameworks and
prompting and guard rails also to help
you with the quality I just talked about
test smells so if we are expecting AI to
be you know being able to like using AI
using llms to kind of guide us not to
fall into pfalls not to do like bad
practices actually I don't know if you
notice like open I just released critic
GPT it's specialized like supposed to be
specialized in that we also have similar
models in COD Mii specializing in
finding smells and problem Etc and then
if you're not you know the top Testing
Engineer developer or you're just tired
and this mistake could cost you then
cover agent supposedly it's still a tool
that needs to to be worked on to be
frank but supposedly also help you to to
apply best practices so these are two
example why using cover agent okay that
was really helpful thanks for telling us
those details about coverage agent one
of the thing that I'm taking from our
conversation so far is that you're still
expecting the software engineer to be in
the loop so to speak when these test
cases are being generated so they can
guide the cover agent tool they can
accept some of the tests and reject
other tests and then they can
iteratively pursue the generation of
test cases is that the right way to
think about it Yes actually I would like
to in high level talk about examples
that this tool would work quite well and
I'm talking about qu with respect to can
it with a click of a button generate a
full test Suite A good one and cases
that it won't and actually like if
you're just expected to with a click of
a button give you a good test weite it
just won't okay and this debate will
actually lead to a point where I believe
that we are quite far at least with the
current ation of cover agent from you
know you need the developer in the loop
and it will stay like that for a long
while and this might lead to when not I
think the profession will evolve but
that's another question so great so I
claim that sometimes four lines of code
like in clean code one method like there
is a very very high chance that you will
find these exact or very similar phone
lines of code somewhere in some open
source even if you think they're special
and by the way A Plus or a minus might
be a big difference but very very
similar if not 100% like we think we're
special I think like software becomes
special in two ways one is how we start
combining like these methods of the four
lines together and sometimes like just
one minus or one plus or something like
that makes a difference okay why did I
mention that practically if you are
doing like small component testing and
these components are relatively simple
they take like simple strings simple
integers you know simple structures and
manipulate them in ways that you expect
to have in the open source even if it's
sophisticated like types of manipulation
you'll be surprised sometimes you will
feel oh my God I just wrote two test I
called cover agent I got 100% code
coverage I actually did it three times
with a different prompt I got three
different test Suites in the future will
also integrate mutation testing Etc so
even tell you which of the three test
sus are better we just talked about
cover
report not being like good enough and
you need to compliment to it so and then
like oh my God you don't need me okay
but although by the way notice that I
did say that you need to come with a one
or two first tests and even in those
cases we can talk about it later if you
want me to but in cases where your code
actually is strongly coupled to Unique
data that is unique for your company is
unique for you know for your software
let's say you know know you're some kind
of like entertainment company and you
have like a special Json don't hate me
if that's the structure that I'm using
now to run through my software and let's
say you have some Json that comes from a
database and you keep flying like
throwing into different parts of your
software to actually like execute what
your business logic you're trying to
achieve if you don't collect it by
yourself and use that part to prompt the
cover agent it has very low chance to
actually being able to do any proper
testing now by the way I want to
challenge myself supposedly you can say
that a lot of this Json structure and
data could be covered from the code if
we're talking about regression test and
we are talking we didn't talk about it
right away we are talking about
regression test right now so because
there are if statements there are
different like string matching Etc so
you could supposedly if you're
intelligent like creature the most
intelligent creature you can infer those
like structure Etc but first lmm are not
sufficient intelligent right now and I
do claim that there will be many cases
that you cannot infer everything from
the code and if you even try to it might
open a too large like space to actually
do proper testing so one reason just as
an example why you can't avoid right now
from working with the developers is that
the developers need to provide
additional information extract it from
the databases extract it from your J
ticket from your specification and
whatever and prompt the cover agent and
then that's the hard work of like the
tedious work of you know writing like
different edge cases according to that
to the cover agent and I claim that just
collecting these data it's not like such
a simple task you need to know which
data you want to collect and why Etc so
we're still being challenged but I think
this is in my opinion the fun part of
the testing like thinking what is the
type of the data I need maybe because
I'm ml dude in my past ml professional
so like thinking what is the data I want
want to provide the cover agent to be
able to generate test for me I think
that's actually where the creativity and
fun generating
test that makes a lot of sense so you've
mentioned that these large language
models are helping the tester to augment
their existing test cases are the llms
running on the tester's computer or are
you leveraging some type of cloud-based
service that provides the llm to the
tester who's using cover agent great so
we Tred to provide a tool that is
generic to the llm it's hard by the way
you will notice like that different
prompts could benefit from getting
better results not just in cover agents
anywhere from different models but we
tried to be very generic as much as we
could and we connected like the light
llm like package the library it's open
source and that enables the user if
you're the developer if you download our
tool from GitHub or installed Etc to
basically choose the model now
interestingly the model right now is
like almost light LM supports almost any
Cloud models but I actually think and
I'm not like you a bit of like change my
confidence but I think that light llm
also support like local models and if
not I believe that integrating o Lama
for example is quite easy to do so just
open Us in the cover agent GitHub hey I
couldn't run it locally and probably
quite quickly we will integrate like ol
or something so any cloud model although
you might need to play and see what
works better for you I think also local
and if not will make it local it's not
an issue quality will be different okay
like this is life like smaller models at
the moment are less good and usually use
smaller models on your computer so when
I tried the tool called cover agent I
was able to integrate with a whole bunch
of different cloudbased llms and we did
use light llm when I was trying out the
tool and talk about that later in our
episode just to be very clear when I'm
doing code coverage testing with cover
agent is it transmitting my code to the
llm that I have picked using the light
llm system and if so what kind of code
does cover agent transmit to the cloud
yeah totally in order to provide good
context for the llm what is given is the
existing test Suite the coverage report
to some extent and also the coder we
want to cover the llm will provide much
better results like one of the mode of
operation for cover agent is to generate
tests that covered lines that are not
yet covered in order to increase the
code coverage therefore the code needs
to be sent to the llm provider in order
to see those lines and the context
around them as much as possible to
actually with a helpful in most cases in
order to pass through this Branch so
definitely the code and the existing
tests would be beneficial that's what
cover agent does as well as like the
coverage report or like data that is
extracted from the coverage report all
right so the light llm tool helps cover
agent interact with a whole bunch of
different cloud-based models you can
also use it with some local models and
it's going to transmit a part of the
existing test suite and maybe the
project source code so that it can
generate new test cases that augment the
test Suite now I think at this point
we've mentioned that there are a whole
bunch of cloud llms like chat GPT or
Claude or GitHub co-pilot before we move
into some of the specifics about the
implementation of cover agent and then
how you actually evaluated it can you
briefly compare it to things like
anthropics clae or GitHub co-pilot or
other tools of that nature yeah of
course okay so with your permission I'll
really shortly talk about like alphac
codium it's another open source tool
that we provided that you can with a
click of a button generate solutions for
code contest competition like for
competitive code competition and do
better than the majority of the
competitors there and that's like
amazing and if you just try GPT 4 or
sonat 3.5 Etc and prompt them even use
the best prompt you can you won't reach
even like half of the accuracy that you
would reach with Alpha codium and the
reason is that Alpha Cod
is more an agentic or if you like what
we call a flow it's like a specific
agentic methodology that is designed to
generate solution for you know simple
competitive programming problems and
within this flow we try to inject the
best practices that you would do as a
developer so it's like built in guard
rails and best practices that you won't
see like out of the box
like Chachi PT or claw AI actually
applying that's why you get the best
result there and now apply the same
notion to cover agent we're trying to
work with this design a flow or actually
meta did it right in their paper to
Perfection IE for this task is the idea
then that somehow cover agent is
collecting information from the products
code base and then making the right
kinds of prompts so that I as a software
engineer don't have to figure out how to
do that when I'm chatting with GitHub
co-pilot or Claude or some other system
like that yeah right there's a slight
like still as an engineer there's
something inaccurate there and I'm going
to fix it but it's correct so before I'm
fixing it you're right like you are
going to use cover agent by stating here
are the components I want to cover
here's how I would run the test suite
and the coverage report and you know
there's a few more like parameters like
what the coverage I want to achieve and
then the cover agent would definitely do
some context collection that basically
would not happen easily with those tools
that we just mentioned but also the
second part is that it will start a flow
that is will not happen but maybe by
chance it will happen with claw there is
some agentic flow but there's higher
chances that a flow that's designed to
to increase code cover generate test
cover agent will do that for you the
only inaccuracy is that the context
collection from your Reaper right now in
cover agent is relatively basic and
that's one of the you know opportunities
to improve it's much more elaborated
than there's no context collection or
relevant one in chpt or claw but here it
is but it's still basic as opposed to
other tools of ours like the ID agent or
the pr agent before we move on to the
next topic can you give a concrete
example of the flow that you had been
referencing a moment ago the Alpha
codium One or or the cover agent one you
could describe it in either cover agent
or Alpha codium because I know they're
both tools to help software Engineers by
using llms but let's start with cover
agent what is the flow that you were
referencing okay so when we came out
with alphac codium we coined the term
like uh flow engineering which was
actually accepted by the industry uh if
I may say like Android car party Etc
what we're saying there is that usually
how we perceive AI empowered system is
what I call like system one syncing
system one systems I'm referring to
Danielle kman unfortunately with us for
like passed away like eight eight months
ago or so it's basically like you give
the system a prompt like a request the
system collects some context like
immediate context and with one inference
we provide the output and that's like
what prompt engineering about even rug
is almost like that like it's just like
a more sophisticated part of of context
on collection in system two thinking
like the system it's not just an
inference is running a full flow that
could have two to like infinite amount
of like prompts usually not just to give
you like a dozen of of prompting and
we'll also use some tools okay and this
flow is not just like a Chain of Thought
or like the react if you're familiar
that just gives the llm the full freedom
to compute in Fair by itself what's the
next step rather it's like almost a
state machine that's why I'm calling it
a flow with edges and each noted you say
what that task needs to be done and flow
engineering is designing that flow and
then interestingly it happens that the
prompt the variance of the accuracy of
the system because changes in the prompt
actually reduces when you're doing only
system one thinking and that's system to
with the system 2 is the full elaborated
system flow then small changes in
prompts could generate really big
differences in in the output you
probably experienced that but if you're
doing flow engineering a lot of the
information and like intelligence is the
flow itself and usually the prompts are
simpler Etc in Alpha codium we put it
simple I'm not going to elaborate too
much right now is we basically designed
a flow that imitates the developer
here's a problem given as an input as a
developer you would reflect on that try
to understand it try to think how would
you test like the solution then think
about a few solution try to think which
is the first you want to try to
implement try to think how would you
test that specific one then implement it
then check it versus test and fix it
generate a few more test fix that and
then output that's exactly by the way
the alpha codium flow in a very simple
way to description that's the flow Alpha
codium the cover agent flow is very
different to put it really simple it
here's a a few test last week parse the
coverage report try to inference which
are the lines you want to Now cover to
enhance the coverage try to generate a
few tests each test check does it run
you know does it pass and does it
increase coverage yes take that test
rerun the coverage report and iterate
okay that's a full flow like putting it
in a simple way wow that was really
helpful that makes a lot of sense and I
think it is a good foundation for us to
dive into more details now we've already
mentioned light llm and I think we get
that that helps the cover agent tool
work with 100 plus large language models
I wanted to briefly talk about the tool
that's called pantic because I notice
that cover agent uses pantic and I think
that pantic may play a role in flow
engineering so can you tell us briefly
what is pantic and how does it work in
the cover agent tool yeah in the most
simple way I think like pantic it helps
you to manage typing like python is not
inherently like very good with with
types as opposed to some other languages
and sometimes it's extremely helpful
that when you pass data to a different
method function Etc like you ensure that
the parameter the variable Etc like
receives the input in a certain with a
certain style in a certain format AKA a
certain type identic helps you manage
that in in different ways and you're
right that if we designed a prompt to
fit for a specific structure and now
like if you ruin it in the middle maybe
the entire flow would be ruined rather
if you kind of stop the flow because of
a type op typing problem or you fix the
type on the way you probably still in
many cases get a good result so that's
like definitely like kind of the guard
rail
an example of a tool that you can
integrate into flows to guardrail the
flow that makes a lot of sense and just
to make sure that listeners are clear
the cover agent system itself is built
in Python and many of the packages that
we're talking about are connected to the
Python programming language although
pedantic is actually now at its core
implemented in Rust I think at this
point itar it might be helpful if we
very quickly comment on the types of
program s for which cover agent can
generate tests if cover agent is
implemented in Python does it only work
for python or can it generate code for
programs in a wide variety of other
languages great so this time I'm going
to simplify with my answer and then I'm
going to fix myself just to keep it
simple at the beginning so copper agent
itself is written in Python but the llm
is the one that generating the code and
your command that you provide as an in
input to run that test to run your
environment to run your code is the one
that actually like needs needs to be in
your in your language Etc so there
there's no theoretical implication or
constraints about which language you
want to apply cover agent on like
program language except that maybe if
this language is too exotic that the
llms were not trained on that but like I
mentioned we did design a flow and it's
includes different prompting and certain
prompts try to deal with different
flavors of testing types testing
properties like for example in Python
you need to have this indentation right
and in other languages there are others
like uh you know you need to have a
setup method in some cases and of
different kinds and you go is specific
about its style Etc and sometimes the
llm will not output proper tests and the
entire idea of cover agents is
automatically generating those running
them checking them so you need LM to
Output proper test to start with and
then like you need to have the prompt
that guides the llm with different
properties and it could be that
different languages would have higher
accuracy less faulty test etc for
example we mostly checked on go and
Python and typescript javascripts so
probably will do really well there I
think the next language Java we we tried
really well last thing and that's
you do need a coverage report and part
of cover agent is parsing the coverage
report okay so that's also kind of
language report like you know elov Joka
what sorry like sometimes I a funny name
I don't say correctly Etc and then so
basically that's another limitation it's
not a real problem like if you don't see
one of the coverage tools there you can
actually go to the open source and try
to write a parser so there's no like a
real limitation rather like a current
status of the the implementation I think
we're covering like elov yako Etc there
there's like three four one one of them
of THS okay so that's like another
limitation that can be overcome really
easily that makes a lot of sense and in
fact it connects to my experience with
using cover agent so when I was using it
to test some of my own python code I
gave it a coverage report in the cobor
XML format and lo and behold it parsed
it perfectly and it was able to generate
test for my project that did in fact
increase coverage so the idea is if I'm
understanding you correctly cover agent
itself doesn't have a coverage tool
inside of it it leverages existing
coverage tools that can produce coverage
reports in existing well-known formats
like the one that comes from kobura or
Joko or other tools of that nature am I
thinking about it the right way yes yes
correct Cur is exactly like one of our
favors you know for example for python
like uh Etc and jako is like uh
definitely like you know the leading
ones but you you probably might have
your own preference that you're using in
the company and you're probably going to
be running them for example as part of
your cicd part of your your build when
you want to like check that your build
is right now like passing all test or
whatever like process that that you have
we definitely didn't want to like create
our own coverage tool and coverage
report rather we wanted to connect to
yours because you probably if you care
about testing and that's why you're
coming to cover agent then you're
probably already using one of these
tools and we we prefer to connect to
them so you won't need to change
anything and these two this tool will be
useful for you sure that makes a lot of
sense now a moment ago I remember you
talking about how it could generate code
for a python project or maybe a go
project and in the context of python the
llm might actually generate a test case
that isn't formatted correctly or in go
it might generate a go test that doesn't
compile so what does cover agent do in
those tricky
situations yeah great so the first thing
that cover agent does in order to accept
to validate a test is actually check if
it if it runs you know runs compiles Etc
and the most basic implementation of
cover agent would just drop that test a
bit more sophisticated implementation of
cover agent would take the output from
the log from the error you know message
and can try to regenerate and fix that
why am I saying with that confidence
because we do have this fix mechanism in
our other tool called Cod youate but in
cover agent maybe until you or already
be there be there but first we wanted to
imitate reproduce the result as much as
we could from the original paper and
that doesn't include that mechanism
right now it's if it doesn't build run
compile like we don't take it but
obviously the more you know
comprehensive solution would be to take
a look on the automatically have cover
agent fetching the error messages and
try to fix you could claim that maybe
it's not the best way to go because who
said that eventually runtime wise and
and cost-wise it's worthwhile to look on
the error but in my opinion it is at
least some kind of one of the routes to
explore because if it didn't run if it
didn't compile actually maybe there is
some gold to dig there to fix that and
reach a new Branch a new line to cover
Etc yeah that's a really good point and
it connects to something that I was
thinking about so in addition to a test
case not compiling or perhaps not being
formatted correctly in the context of
python and pest it may be that the test
case is failing so does cover agent
distinguish between a test case that is
failing because it found a bug and a
test case that was failing because it
wasn't set up correctly or something
like that yeah okay so right now cover
agent similar to the paper that you know
it tried to reproduce is only doing
regression test
and this is very valuable for example
let's assume that you're an EDI team
developing a lot of code and you don't
have time to create regression test at
some point usually there are builds that
you have very high confidence about them
so much quicker than you would imagine
you can generate a lot of regression
test and then moving forward you would
know if you're breaking something or not
so regression test although their value
is limited in certain cases it could be
like
invaluable now considering that that
we're focusing on regression test if a
test pass like we do want it that's a
short answer having said that It's
Tricky a test can actually pass if like
the logic is bad and the code is bad and
the tests can pass if the logic is bad
but actually the assert we talked about
in the beginning what checks if the
result is right is bad so actually it's
very trick tricky and this is like
different technology can be applied to
try to prove that actually there fields
and areas it's not just two and two it's
not bad code good code bad test good
test and you know things like that
actually it opens up to A Whole New
World of what's a bad test bad assert
bad logic bad data so it could be like a
lot of problems there but the most
simple implementation right now is
regression test and considering that we
did proper prompting and if it passed we
want it by the way that's also one of
the reason you want a human reviewer at
the end like what we talked about the
beginning wow that's a really good
response and I see exactly what you're
getting at and clearly generating test
cases or augmenting a test Suite
automatically is a really tricky task to
get exactly right because sometimes test
cases may be passing but for
coincidental reasons and in other cases
they may be failing but if you're going
to focus on regression testing ideally
you want to confirm the existing
behavior and you want to increase
coverage when possible is that the right
idea yes okay good now one of the things
that I think about when I'm writing my
own test cases is that sometimes I have
to write mock objects does cover agent
actually generate these various types of
mocks or
spies overall can cover agent make test
scaffolding for me I would say that MOX
is one of the most challenging Parts
like I think that also what you hinted
like with with proper testing because
there's you know you want a test to be
fast and they're not flaky and things
like that but there's also problem with
marks maybe it's not like proper testing
of your real production case Etc I like
it's really really challenging okay
that's a side note why I think it is
important right now specifically for
cover agent I'm not talking about our
other agents mocks are treated very
simple in a simple way if you provide
mocks as part of your simple test Suite
they would be uh considered otherwise
you need to in most cases I'm not saying
it's still AI a statistical creature it
might generate marcks although it's not
being prompt to that but in most cases
if you didn't provide it as part of your
like original small test we that you're
trying to enhance then you need to
provide a proper prompt like although
cover agent is a tool and a flow and not
you know a Q&A there's still a mechanism
actually two mechanisms to prompt a
cover agent one is by providing
additional data in files Etc we talk
about part of the reasoning for that for
example if you actually want to provide
like data that is expected like because
your software is complicated and and the
input is coming from some database or
something that the llm won't be able to
think of the other is like more
traditional it's weird to say
traditional but more traditional
prompting and we manage manage to inject
that into a flow and not a Q&A so you
can use these two mechanisms to try to
influence cover agent to create mocks
because the def is is kind of off and it
might do a good job rally speaking
comparing to and when need to say
compared to what but to tools that are
professional in generating mocks maybe
not as good but comparing to like a
simple like chat GP or something like
that before we move on to the
categorization of tests that cover agent
May generate remember that a moment ago
you talked about something called a
flaky test so briefly can you tell the
listeners what is a flaky test and then
how does cover agent handle flaky test
cases that may be returned by the large
language model this time I'm going to
give an example to explain what is a
flaky test if you have a test and you're
running it five times and it doesn't
give you the same result each time
especially if sometimes it pass
sometimes it fails that's the most
obvious flakiness then it flak
it means how how can you trust that test
if it passed four time the same test
test you know just run it five times and
and pass four time and and fail one
that's a flaky test llms you can try to
prompt it not to generate the flaky test
actually I think the prompting to start
with will try to do that because there
are test smells that can be smelled for
example if there is an obvious API call
an obvious one if the API fails let's
say like I'm going to take the simplest
again example here like you're calling
like exchange API from dollars to Euro
or something like that and that could be
flaky then you're flaking your test for
no reason and that's like an ideal place
for example in my opinion there could be
exceptional reason to put a mock or for
example so like LM will try to help you
with that if you prompted but there's a
lot of responsibility still in on
developer to run cover agent on
components that or in a way that to
start with like checking independent
like components or independent
microservices Etc to reduce the
flakiness and again another
responsibility yet for the developer
okay so it sounds like down the road
cover agent might be able to do things
like rerun the test Suite or look at
Deltas of coverage or things of that
nature but in part it still is the
responsibility of the software engineer
to think carefully about which
components they ask cover agent to test
and then to look at the test cases and
to assess whether they're good ones or
not correct I'm not saying that in five
years or so there won't be systems that
will take more and more parts for
example full code analysis of your code
base and then suggesting you as a
developer here are five areas five
components and two microservices and one
endtoend system that we were recommend
you to run ABCD tools one of them is a
cover agent and then you're almost like
you know like orchestrator Etc and that
will come with an analysis of which part
of your codebase would probably be less
flaky and also very important to test
Etc but right now I think like although
at CI we are developing things like that
they they're not as mature developers
are being needed again like I just
hinted that even in five years being
needed but right now they're needed for
different reason more fundamental like
stuff like you just mentioned of course
what you're saying definitely makes
sense and it connects to my experiences
with codium and also with cover agent
one of the things that I wanted to
briefly touch on is that when cover
agent was creating tests for me
automatically I noticed that it would
categorize the test as like a happy path
test or an exception test and I didn't
do that the tool did it for me
automatically so what are those types of
tests and how does the tool will
actually categorize them in that way
okay think about we talk about code
coverage right we talked about the fact
that if you cover more lines of your
code that is you ran test that ran
executed a certain line then you
probably have the lower chance to to
that you have a bug in that run through
that line that means that if you want to
cover like 100% of the line just as an
example we talked about the problem with
the symetric cover 100 lines also you
need to have the right assert Etc I'm
going to repeat that it's important then
you would want to go over many different
behaviors of your code many different
edge cases Etc and the part of the flow
and the prompting flow engineering we
did and the prompt engineering we did in
cover agent and that's only going to be
enhanced as we progress through time and
techniques that tries to generate you
know these happy paths edge cases Etc to
cover more and more parts more lines Etc
and I think developers appreciate when
the thinking of an agent is being
exposed that you notice those properties
and you you and because we said that for
example developers need to review the
output it helps you to review it review
it more easily by the way when I'm
talking about flow engineering for
example what I mentioned for example in
order to catch not only more edge cases
but strong edge cases I might want to
run mutation testing and then and other
tools okay so that's like and we will
output codium cover agent will output
some of these so you could be amazed
engaged and also and make it easier for
you to to review the output so I think
this is the second or third time that
you've mentioned mutation testing my
impression is that it's not yet
integrated into cover agent but to make
sure our episode is now self-contained
can you briefly talk about what it is
and then what steps you might take to
integrate mutation testing into cover
agent yeah by the way I love to do that
and maybe that's a good call to action
we open source cover agent and you can
use it and we'll be happy and we do have
a lot of contribution by the way from
the community like single developers as
as well as like companies Etc I want to
encourage everyone here to contribute
and I think one of those especially for
professionals that you know worked with
mutation testing that's one of those
contribution we would love to see that
we provided a road map there are
different type of mutation testing I am
going to simplify a bit Al it's hard for
me not to be accurate I probably wasn't
accurate many places to simplify thing
I'm going to do that again here there
roughly speaking there are two types of
mutations given a test suite and given a
code you want to test you can one so
type one mutate the test type two mutate
the code let's talk about type two let's
say I have a test Suite that supposedly
cover 85% of the lines
and let's say I have a second test Suite
that also cover 80% of the line how do I
know which test Suite is better it could
be that they even covering the same
lines but they're very different tests
actually could be different tests
mutation testing type two the one that
mutates the code could help if I let's
start with something simple random
randomly mutate the code and the test
Suite is not failing like let's say you
start with like all the tests are
passing and the test Suite does not fail
any test the tests are probably let's
say mutate a lot the test Suite is
probably not strong the test Suite that
actually fails more tests as I mutate
the code is probably stronger because
it's catching more more of the code
notice a few hyperparameters here do I
randomly mutate the code how many
mutation I'm doing which type of
mutation these are part of the thing
that in the past we would do
heuristically with some algorithms and
actually llms is one of those like llms
can help us improve like performance on
that part I believe you you can imagine
what type one it's different like here
you m mutate the test I'll stop here let
me know if to dive on double click on
that okay thanks for that description of
mutation testing I'm sure that will be
helpful to the listeners as we start to
draw our episode to a conclusion I want
to let them know that they should check
the show notes because in the show notes
we'll reference the foundations of
software engineering paper that was by
researchers and engineers at meta that
was ultimately the inspiration for
building the cover agent tool what I
want to do now is briefly turn our
attention to some of the lessons that
we've learned today so for example we've
talked about automated test augmentation
we've talked about the role that the
large language model should play in this
process and I'm wondering can you share
a little bit about some of the lessons
that you have learned when you've been
building cover agent or the alpha codium
system or some of the other commercial
products that are coming out of codium
AI what have you learned about developer
productivity and building good developer
tools great so I'll shortly relate to
one learning around like building those
tools and one learning about like using
developers productivity tools so about
developing them there could be could be
like it's a talk by itself but I do want
to iterate on the flow engineering like
don't try to build a tool that all it
all it does quotequote like prompt
collect context prompt and LM output try
to build a full system that evolves like
an algorithm a flow that includes like
guard rails and inject best practices
that fits for what you're building okay
and and that creates higher accuracy and
results as well as less lower variants
either of the system or of your prompt
that that you're injecting and by the
way I think this also projects to any
other tool that you're using with AI
okay try to think about flows when
you're building a tool for physician or
for lawyers or Etc about Dev tools I
think like developers love writing code
they love building and now they can you
know use code completion to do even a
bit more probably save time and go drink
more coffee I don't think it's really
helpful for generating more features but
actually let's think about the real
bottlenecks I don't think it's writing
more lines of code it's about code
quality it's about code reviewing it's
about testing Etc so I think that when
you want to start uh integrating you
know different AI Dev tools to improve
your productivity actually think what
are your today bottlenecks and what are
your today problems for example if you
look on your you know Sprint and you see
50% of your task is bugs solving do you
really think that adding codee
completion will help you to deal with
that probably you need to find how AI
tools can be injected into your workflow
to reduce the amount of bugs to reduce
the quality Etc so that's my main
suggestion don't think about the tools
think about your pains and problems and
then search for the existing tools to
try to try to Sol that wow this has been
an awesome conversation and what you
said a moment ago was really
thought-provoking
if listeners want to learn more about
some of the things that we've talked
about today like GitHub co-pilot they
can refer to episode 533 of software
engineering radio I'll also link you to
some other episodes where we've covered
some Affiliated Concepts but with those
points in mind now that we've talked
about alphac codium and cover agent and
you've given us a call to action is
there anything that we haven't yet
covered that you'd like to share I just
want to say uh that I really enjoyed you
know very detailed discussion about the
cover agent and that what I want to
encourage people is to play with these
kinds of tools play with them like the
the profession I'm not saying it's going
to evolve tomorrow but it's going to
evolve try downloading these tools
playing with them like cover agent is
literally like one minute to run and
you'll notice that there is one part
that is hard to actually navigate is
that command that you need to provide to
cover agent on how you want your test to
to run in your environment because the
idea that cover range needs to run you
know in the environment where the
component needs to run and then it will
take you 15 more minutes okay you
probably have the environment to some
extent and then like with an hour you
don't don't stop yourself try these kind
kind of kind of tool like cover agent
and do that in my opinion weekly because
some of them like suddenly going to have
like Lea frog like effect and you want
to have those in in Your Arsenal as a
developer everyone all M developers I
think are going to be AI Empower
developers in the very near future yeah
that's a great point I want to emphasize
for our listeners that you can download
the cover agent tool from GitHub and I
tried it out and itar I have to agree it
was super fun I tried it with a whole
bunch of different llms I tried it on
different projects I tried it for
different languages and it was super
cool to see it generating all of those
test cases for me and in some cases I
could integrate them into my existing
test Suite so let me say thank you for
this conversation and additionally let
me say thank you for open sourcing the
cover agent tool it's been a lot of fun
for me to try it and it's been great for
me to chat with you today is there
anything else you'd like to pass along
to our listeners before we conclude the
episode I know thank you so much well
thank you for talking today this is
Gregory cap Hammer signing off for
software engineering radio goodbye
everyone thank you
Gregory thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
It software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at
e-r. to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SE radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening